Guide to the Philip Barry Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Philip Barry papers
1917-1950
YCAL MSS 414
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
22.28
(54 boxes)
The Philip Barry Papers document Barry's development and career as a playwright, from his earliest production at Yale in 1919 to his final work in 1949. The Papers are composed chiefly of Barry's notes, sketches, and drafts of his plays, materials relating to the production and publication of his plays, and correspondence with friends, family, fans, and colleagues in the worlds of theater and literature. Additional materials are also present, including scripts of plays by other authors, college and workshop notes, press clippings, and pamphlets and photographs relating to professional and social organizations.
Barry, Philip, 1896-1949
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Ellen Barry, 1940-1961 and from unidentified sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on microfilm. Consult Access Services for further information.
Philip Barry (1896-1949)
Philip Jerome Quinn Barry (1896-1949) was a 20th-century American playwright most widely known for comedies he authored during the 1920s and 1930s, including Paris Bound (1927), Holiday (1928), and The Philadelphia Story (1939). Born in Rochester, New York, Barry was the third and youngest son of a successful Irish immigrant father and an Irish-American mother from Philadelphia. After graduating from Yale in 1919, Barry attended George Pierce Baker's legendary 47 Workshop at Harvard, where he won the prestigious Richard Herndon Prize in 1922 for The Jilts. Subsequently produced by Herndon on Broadway as You and I, this script was the first of several composed before1930 that would establish Barry's reputation for high comedy and repartee. Together with the comedies of manners for which he was most popularly received, Barry authored a number of serious dramas tending toward religious and existential themes, including Tomorrow and Tomorrow (1931) and the more experimental Hotel Universe (1930) and Here Come the Clowns (1938). Barry's career as a playwright peaked in 1939 with the production of The Philadelphia Story, starring Katharine Hepburn, which was adapted to the screen the following year in a film featuring Hepburn, James Stewart, and Cary Grant.
Barry married Ellen Semple (1898-1995) in 1922. The two divided their time primarily between their homes in Manhattan and Mount Kisco, New York. They were the parents of two sons, Philip Semple Barry and Jonathan Peter Barry, and a daughter who died in infancy in 1933. Philip Barry died of a heart attack in 1949 at the age of 53.
Scope and Contents
The Philip Barry Papers document Barry's development and career as a playwright, from his earliest production at Yale in 1919 to his final work in 1949. The Papers are composed chiefly of Barry's notes, sketches, and drafts of his plays, materials relating to production and publication, and correspondence with friends, family, fans, and colleagues in the worlds of theater and literature. Additional materials are also present, including scripts of plays by other authors, college and workshop notes, press clippings, and pamphlets and photographs relating to professional and social organizations.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Writings, 1918 - circa 1949. II. Subject Files, 1921-1949. III. Correspondence, 1921-1949. IV. Other Papers, 1917-1950. V. Plays by Others, 1933-1941.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; American drama -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century; Playwriting; Theater -- Production and direction -- United States; Theater -- United States; Theater scripts; Photographic prints; Authors; Dramatists; Barry, Philip, 1896-1949
- Writings, 1918 - circa 1949; Series I; 17.64 linear feet (42 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title. Within titles, files are arranged in roughly chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains versions of works by Philip Barry in various stages of completion, including thirty plays, two screenplays, one opera libretto, one novel, and one short story. The material includes notes and sketches (holograph, typescript, and carbon, some corrected), final scripts (carbon), and proofs (some corrected) of these writings.
  - The Animal Kingdom, 1931; 5 (Box 1)
  - The Animal Kingdom, 1931; 5 (Box 2)
  - The Animal Kingdom, 1931; 2 (Box 3)
  - Bright Star, 1934; 6 (Box 3)
  - Bright Star, circa 1934; 5 (Box 4)
  - Bright Star, circa 1934; 10 (Box 5)
  - Bright Star, circa 1934; 7 (Box 6)
  - Cock Robin, circa 1927; 2 (Box 6)
  - Cock Robin, circa 1927 (Box 7)
  - The Dollar
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Holiday
  - The Emperor of China
    See: My Name Is Aquilon
  - Figure of a Girl
  - Foolish Notion, circa 1945; 6 (Box 7)
  - Foolish Notion, circa 1945; 2 (Box 8)
  - Foolish Notion, 1945; 9 (Box 9)
  - Gentle Reader (circa 1934)
    See: Bright Star
  - Gentle Reader (circa 1939)
    See: The Philadelphia Story
  - Gold for Davy Jones, 1935 (Box 10)
  - The Gorgeous Hussy, 1935 (Box 10)
  - Hail and Farewell
    See: Tomorrow and Tomorrow
  - A Happy Man
    See: In a Garden
  - Here Come the Clowns, circa 1938; 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Here Come the Clowns, circa 1938; 9 folders (Box 11)
  - Here Come the Clowns, circa 1938; 4 folders (Box 12)
  - The History of Clancy
    See: Here Come the Clowns
  - The High Hand, circa 1920-1924; 7 (Box 12)
  - The High Hand, circa 1924; 13 (Box 13)
  - Holiday, circa 1928; 5 (Box 14)
  - Homage to Honor
  - Hotel Universe, circa 1930 (Box 14)
  - Hotel Universe, circa 1930; 5 (Box 15)
  - Hotel Universe, circa 1930; 9 (Box 16)
  - In a Garden, 1924; 5 (Box 17)
  - In a Garden, 1924; 12 (Box 18)
  - The Jilts
    See: You and I
  - John, circa 1927; 9 (Box 19)
  - The Joyous Season, circa 1933-1934; 8 folders (Box 20)
  - The Joyous Season, 1934; 4 (Box 21)
  - The Joyous Season, 1934; 2 (Box 22)
  - The Joyous Season, 1934 (Box 22)
  - Kingdom Come
    See: John
  - Liberty Jones, circa 1941; 2 (Box 22)
  - Liberty Jones, circa 1941; 6 (Box 23)
  - Liberty Jones, circa 1941; 9 (Box 24)
  - Liberty Jones, circa 1941; 5 (Box 25)
  - Liberty Jones, circa 1941 (Box 26)
  - The Man in the Street
    See: White Wings
  - A Man of Taste
  - Meadow's End (short story), circa 1922; 3 (Box 26)
  - My Name Is Aquilon, circa 1949; 6 folders (Box 26)
  - My Name Is Aquilon, circa 1949; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Nancy Stair, circa 1934; 4 (Box 27)
  - Nancy Stair, circa 1934; 3 (Box 28)
  - No Thoroughfare, 1918 (Box 28)
  - Oh Promise Me
    See: The High Hand
  - Paris Bound, 1927; 4 (Box 29)
  - The Philadelphia Story, circa 1939; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - The Philadelphia Story, 1939-1941; 7 folders (Box 30)
  - The Philadelphia Story, 1941 (Box 30)
  - The Philadelphia Story (screenplay), 1940; 1 (Box 30)
  - Point of View
    See: Foolish Notion
  - Poor Richard
    See: The Youngest
  - Second Threshold, circa 1949; 8 folders (Box 31)
  - The Son of One
  - Spring Dance, circa 1936 (Box 31)
  - The Stern Daughter
    See: Second Threshold
  - Sweet Chariot
  - The Stagger System, 1941; 5 (Box 32)
  - Ten Scars Make a Man, 1923 (Box 32)
  - This Time Sadly
    See: The Animal Kingdom
  - The Tin Bridge
    See: Liberty Jones
  - Tom Thumb, undated (Box 32)
  - Tomorrow and Tomorrow, circa 1930; 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Tomorrow and Tomorrow, circa 1930; 6 folders (Box 33)
  - Tomorrow and Tomorrow, 1930 (Box 34)
  - Transient, 1918 (Box 34)
  - War in Heaven (novel), circa 1938; 5 (Box 34)
  - War in Heaven (novel), circa 1938; 3 (Box 35)
  - Westminster Abbey
  - White Wings, circa 1926; 3 (Box 35)
  - White Wings, circa 1926; 8 (Box 36)
  - White Wings (opera libretto), circa 1935; 2 (Box 36)
  - The Wild Harps Playing
  - Without Love, circa 1942; 9 (Box 37)
  - Without Love, circa 1942; 12 (Box 38)
  - Without Love, circa 1942 (Box 38)
  - Without Love (screenplay), 1944 (Box 39)
  - You and I, circa 1922; 3 (Box 39)
  - The Youngest, circa 1922-1924; 3 (Box 39)
  - The Youngest, 1922 - circa 1924; 8 (Box 40)
  - The Youngest, circa 1924; 8 (Box 41)
  - The Youngest, circa 1924; 7 (Box 42)
- Subject Files, 1921-1949; Series II; 1.68 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  This series contains files relating to the production and publication of Barry's plays and other writings. Materials include contracts, box office and royalty statements, budgets, bills, receipts, theater ephemera, and correspondence relating to specific works.
  - The Animal Kingdom, 1931-1947; 3 folders (Box 43)
  - Bright Star, 1934-1935 (Box 43)
  - Cock Robin, 1928-1948 (Box 43)
  - Foolish Notion, 1945 (Box 43)
  - Hail and Farewell
  - Here Come the Clowns, 1935-1943 (Box 43)
  - The High Hand, 1921-1922 (Box 43)
  - Holiday, 1928-1947 (Box 43)
  - Hotel Universe, 1930-1938; 2 (Box 44)
  - In a Garden, 1925 (Box 44)
  - The Jilts
  - John, 1946 (Box 44)
  - The Joyous Season, 1929-1935; 5 folders (Box 44)
  - Liberty Jones, 1931-1935 (Box 44)
  - Liberty Jones, 1940-1942 (Box 45)
  - Meadow's End (short story), 1922 (Box 45)
  - Nancy Stair, 1934 (Box 45)
  - No Thoroughfare, 1919 (Box 45)
  - Paris Bound, 1928-1938 (Box 45)
  - The Philadelphia Story, 1939-1941; 3 folders (Box 45)
  - Poor Richard
  - A Punch for Judy
  - Spring Dance, 1938-1949 (Box 45)
  - Tomorrow and Tomorrow, 1930-1939, 1948 (Box 45)
  - Tomorrow and Tomorrow, 1931-1933; 2 folders (Box 46)
  - War in Heaven (novel), 1938 (Box 46)
  - White Wings, 1930-1946 (Box 46)
  - Without Love, 1943-1944 (Box 46)
  - You and I, 1922-1925 (Box 46)
  - The Youngest, 1923-1925, 1940 (Box 46)
- Correspondence, 1921-1949; Series III; 1.26 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Outgoing correspondence and telegrams to and from Barry are grouped separately at the end of the series, each arranged alphabetically.
  This series consists of personal and business correspondence to and from Philip Barry in the form of holograph and typescript letters (mostly signed), telegrams, and holograph drafts of telegrams. The correspondence relates chiefly to the writing, publication, and productions of Barry's plays. Much of this content is from writers, actors, publishers, and producers sending notes of encouragement and congratulations to Barry, and it extends to letters of appreciation from audiences, discussions of published reviews, and requests for work. Most of the remaining correspondence is of a more personal nature, primarily from Barry's immediate family members and close friends.
  - "A" General, 1923-1949 (Box 47)
  - Adams, Samuel Hopkins, 1935 (Box 47)
  - Author's League, 1944-1949 (Box 47)
  - "B" General, 1932-1944 (Box 47)
  - Baker, George Pierce, 1922-1923 (Box 47)
  - Barry, Agnes M. (sister), 1935-1949? (Box 47)
  - Barry, James (brother), 1935-1944 (Box 47)
  - Barry, Philip, Jr. (son), 1935-1944 (Box 47)
  - Barry Family (miscellaneous), 1923-1944, undated (Box 47)
  - Benét Family, 1936-1944, undated (Box 47)
  - Boyle, Kay, 1932 (Box 47)
  - Brandt and Brandt, 1935-1943 (Box 47)
  - "C" General, 1933-1948 (Box 47)
  - Canby, Henry S., 1922-1934 (Box 47)
  - Carroll, Madeleine, undated (Box 47)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1922 (Box 47)
  - Cornell, Katharine, 1935 (Box 47)
  - Coward-McCann, 1934-1939 (Box 47)
  - Cronyn, Hume, 1934 (Box 47)
  - "D" General, 1922-1942 (Box 47)
  - Daly, James, 1943-1944 (Box 47)
  - DeMille, Agnes, 1935 (Box 47)
  - Dowling, Eddie, 1938-1939 (Box 47)
  - "E" General, 1934-1944 (Box 47)
  - Erskine, John, 1934 (Box 47)
  - Essex, Harry, 1942 (Box 47)
  - "F" General, 1922-1944 (Box 47)
  - Fadiman, Clifton, 1934 (Box 47)
  - Farrar, John, 1942-1944 (Box 47)
  - Forrestal, James, 1944 (Box 47)
  - French, Samuel, 1926-1949 (Box 47)
  - "G" General, 1925-1939 (Box 47)
  - Gallagher, William Francis, 1933-1948 (Box 47)
  - Gassner, John, 1934 (Box 47)
  - Gill, Brendan M., 1935 (Box 47)
  - Gish, Lillian, undated (Box 47)
  - Griffith, Edward H., 1934-1935 (Box 48)
  - "H" General, 1931-1944 (Box 48)
  - Helburn, Theresa, 1922-1949 (Box 48)
  - Hepburn, Katharine, 1938, undated (Box 48)
  - Hopkins, Arthur, 1925-1943 (Box 48)
  - Hopkins, Harry L., 1944 (Box 48)
  - Howard, Sidney, 1935, undated (Box 48)
  - Huston, Walter, 1934 (Box 48)
  - "I" General, 1934-1935, undated (Box 48)
  - "J" General, 1934, undated (Box 48)
  - James, Alice, 1932 (Box 48)
  - Joyce-Selznick Productions, 1935 (Box 48)
  - "K" General, 1922-1935 (Box 48)
  - Kahn, Otto H., 1931-1932 (Box 48)
  - Kaufman, George S., 1940 (Box 48)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1935 (Box 48)
  - Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1940 (Box 48)
  - "L" General, 1932-1947, undated (Box 48)
  - Langner, Lawrence, 1939-1945 (Box 48)
  - Lovett, Robert A., 1934-1947 (Box 48)
  - Luce, Henry R., 1935 (Box 48)
  - "M" General, 1919-1949 (Box 48)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1932-1944 (Box 48)
  - Marshall, Armina, 1943 (Box 48)
  - Maugham, W. Somerset, 1948 (Box 48)
  - Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, 1935 (Box 48)
  - Moore, Douglas, 1949, undated (Box 48)
  - "N" General, 1922-1944 (Box 48)
  - "O" General, 1935-1949 (Box 48)
  - Odets, Clifford, 1935 (Box 48)
  - Oenslager, Donald, 1933 (Box 48)
  - O'Hara, John, undated (Box 48)
  - "P" General, 1933-1947, undated (Box 48)
  - Pemberton, Bruce, 1921, undated (Box 48)
  - Phelps, William Lyon, 1922-1943 (Box 48)
  - Priestly, J.B., 1940 (Box 48)
  - "Q" General, 1933-1944 (Box 48)
  - "R" General, 1933-1943 (Box 48)
  - Reynolds, Quentin, 1922, undated (Box 48)
  - Rice, Elmer, 1934 (Box 48)
  - Rodgers, Richard, 1944 (Box 48)
  - Ross, Harold Wallace, 1942 (Box 48)
  - "S" General, 1922-1948 (Box 48)
  - Shubert, Lee, 1942 (Box 49)
  - Strudwick, Sheppherd, undated (Box 49)
  - "T" General, 1935-1944, undated (Box 49)
  - Thalberg, Irving G., 1934 (Box 49)
  - Theatre Guild, 1939-1942 (Box 49)
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1943 (Box 49)
  - "V" General, 1934-1935, undated (Box 49)
  - Van Druten, John, 1942 (Box 49)
  - "W" General, 1925-1944, undated (Box 49)
  - Wanger, Walter F., 1934 (Box 49)
  - Wilder, Thornton and Isabel Wilder, 1942-1945 (Box 49)
  - Williams, Wayland Wells, undated (Box 49)
  - "Y" General, undated (Box 49)
  - Yale University organizations, 1922-1935, undated (Box 49)
  - Unidentified, 1935-1949, undated (Box 49)
  - Outgoing correspondence (original), 1940 (Box 49)
  - Outgoing correspondence (carbons and drafts), 1923-1947; 2 (Box 49)
  - Incoming telegrams, 1923-1949, undated; 4 (Box 49)
  - Outgoing telegrams and drafts, 1923-1947; 3 (Box 49)
- Other Papers, 1917-1950; Series IV; 1.34 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  This series consists of professional and personal papers existing in a variety of formats. The professional papers include statements and agreements with theaters and professional asssociations, legal literature pertaining to the taxation of authors' income, and notes, drafts, and clippings relating to Barry's plays. Personal papers include college class notes in notebooks and index cards, family correspondence, pamphlets, photographs, deposited checks, and other related material.
  - Agreement draft, Authors' Corporation, Play Producing Department, circa 1935 (Box 50)
  - Bills, price lists, and other papers relating chiefly to personal purchases, 1932-1939, undated (Box 50)
  - Production cost statements, Theatre Guild, 1939-1941 (Box 50)
  - Signed agreement, Dramatists' Guild, 1934 (Box 50)
  - Royalty schedules, Dramatists' Guild, 1944 (Box 50)
  - Royalty statements, 1933-1944; 6 (Box 50)
  - Membership dues statement, Authors League of America, 1949 (Box 50)
  - Academic records and other school-related papers, Philip Barry Jr. and Jonathan Barry, 1934-1936, undated (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous notes and drafts, undated (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, photographs, and ephemera, 1934, 1944, undated (Box 50)
  - Letters to and drawings by Marian White, 1917-1918, undated (Box 51)
  - Correspondence and other papers relating mostly to employment at the U.S. Embassy in London, 1918-1920 (Box 51)
  - Class notes, 1919? (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous notes, drafts, and clippings, circa 1920-1944 (Box 51)
  - Correspondence and other papers relating to plays by Barry, 1922-1930 (Box 51)
  - Ephemera and photographs relating to social organizations in the arts, 1930-1942 (Box 51)
  - Notebook inscribed with notes and ideas, 1931 (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1932-1950 (Box 51)
  - Financial papers, 1934-1935 (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, circa 1934-1942 (Box 51)
  - Speech on playwriting, circa 1936 (Box 51)
  - Correspondence relating to plays by Barry, 1936-1940 (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, notes, and sketches, 1943, undated (Box 51)
  - Legal papers relating to taxation of authors (Goldsmith Case), 1944 (Box 51)
  - L'Empereur de Chine (2 editions), Fernand Léger, 1929, 1948 (Box 51)
  - Notes for 2 comedies, undated (Box 52)
  - Index cards inscribed with notes relating to playwriting, undated (Box 52)
  - Notebooks and loose leaves inscribed with notes and ideas, undated (Box 52)
  - Loose manuscript and typescript leaves of various scripts, undated (Box 52)
  - Blank folio scrapbook, titled in gilt on the cover, "P. B. Without Love ", circa 1944 (Box 53)
- Plays by Others, 1933-1941, undated; Series V; 0.42 linear feet (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by author's name.
  This series consists of a collection of nine carbon scripts of plays by authors other than Philip Barry.
  - Bus-Fakete, Laszlo. Reunion, 1941 (Box 54)
  - Cushing, Tom. The Laughter of the Gods, undated (Box 54)
  - Cushing, Tom. The Old Adam, undated (Box 54)
  - Garrett, Oliver H. P., and Fritz Lang. Hell Afloat, 1935 (Box 54)
  - Grant, James Edward. A Lady Comes to Burkburnett, 1938 (Box 54)
  - Karr, Geoffrey. In a Green Garden (parody of In a Garden ), undated (Box 54)
  - Langner, Lawrence. The Pursuit of Happiness, 1933 (Box 54)
  - Winter, Keith. Ringmaster, 1935 (Box 54)
  - Wylie, Max, and Milton Geiger. Bed Rock, 1941 (Box 54)